Lea Verou^{CV}

Wikipedia • lea.verou.me • @LeaVerou • Github

SUMMARY

I'm currently pursuing a PhD at MIT, doing research in Human-Computer Interaction, specifically end-user programming for creating web applications. In the recent past, I have written an advanced CSS book that became a bestseller in its area, worked at W3C/MIT, gave over 60 talks at web development conferences in 5 continents, and started several popular open source projects. I'm also an Invited Expert in the W3C CSS Working Group, an honor currently extended to only 7 people worldwide.

WORK EXPERIENCE

INDUSTRY

2011–2012 2013-2014	Speaker, author • <u>lea.verou.me</u> Speaking, writing, doing corporate training and workshops about open web standards. Occasionally freelancing.
2012-2013	Developer Relations • <u>W3C/MIT</u> Educating web professionals about open web standards and facilitating community input for W3C specifications under development.
2008–2011	Co-founder, lead web-developer & designer • Fresset Ltd Created the successful Greek community e-steki.gr, which regularly receives over 400,000 visits and 2,500,000 pageviews per month.

ACADEMIC

2014-PRESENT	Research Assistant • Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)
2010-2012	Teaching Assistant • <u>AUEB</u>

Co-designed every aspect of the "Web Technologies and Programming" 4th year undergraduate course, including syllabus and coursework, taught the labs, guest lectured the CSS parts. [Details]

SPEAKING

I have given **over 60 talks in five continents** and spoken at some of the **most prominent international** web development conferences, including <u>SXSW</u>, <u>An Event Apart</u>, <u>Future Of Web Design</u>, <u>JSConf EU</u> and <u>JSConf.asia</u>, <u>CSSConf, Web Directions</u>, <u>Fronteers</u>, <u>TXJS</u>, <u>O'Reilly Fluent</u>

My talks get **enthusiastic reviews**, by both attendees and field experts. My "CSS3 secrets" talk was listed in net magazine's 15 best talks of 2011. My "The humble border-radius" talk was shortlisted in The net awards 2014 as "Conference Talk of the Year". For more information, please refer to the:"Speaking" section on my website.

I have also helped organize W3Conf 2013 and CSSConf 2014.

INDUSTRY RECOGNITION

- Invited Expert at the <u>W3C CSS Working Group</u>, which defines and extends the CSS language.
- Finalist for **The net Awards 2011** in the "**Brilliant newcomer**" category and for **The net Awards 2014** in the "**Outstanding contribution**" and "**Conference Talk of the Year**" categories
- Active follower base of 65,000+ people on twitter and 7,000+ on Github.
- Interviewed by leading industry media, such as .net magazine, Sitepoint, CSS-Tricks, The Big Web Show and The Web Ahead
- My work has been featured by almost every significant website & magazine in the industry. I collect some of these mentions in <u>the "Press" section on my website</u>.

JUDGING & REVIEWING

- Judge in The .net Awards 2011 and 2014.
- Member of <u>Smashing Magazine</u>'s Experts Panel.
- Invited "expert judge" for Mozilla's DevDerby monthly competitions (2011-2012).
- Program committee for O'Reilly Velocity EU conference 2012 and O'Reilly Fluent conference 2012. Advisory Board for O'Reilly Fluent conference 2014.
- Technical reviewer for O'Reilly. I have reviewed "Maintainable JavaScript" by Nicholas Zakas and "JavaScript Web Applications" by Alex MacCaw.
- Past <u>AWWWARDS</u> jury.

PUBLICATIONS

BOOKS

- CSS Secrets, O'Reilly Media
 - Average of **4.9/5** on <u>Amazon</u>, over 50 reviews.
 - Consistently in the <u>top 10 Amazon bestsellers on CSS</u> and the <u>top 15 on User Experience & Usability</u>, since its publication date.
 - Over 700 positive reviews on Twitter.
- Chapter in <u>Smashing Book #3</u> (with David Storey): "Restyle, Recode, Reimagine With CSS3"

ARTICLES

I have written articles for some of the biggest industry media, including <u>A List Apart</u>, <u>Smashing Magazine</u>, <u>24 Ways</u>, <u>net magazine</u>. You can find a more complete list <u>on my website</u>.

SPECIFICATIONS

■ Co-editor of the W3C specification <u>CSS Backgrounds & Borders Level 4</u>

SELECTED PROJECTS

	,
FEB 2015	<u>Awesomplete</u> : Lightweight, simple, ultra extensible autocomplete 4000 stars on Github in its first week, featured on Github's weekly Github Explore newsletter.
JUL 2012	<u>Prism</u> : A beautiful, standards-compliant, extensible syntax highlighter
	23,000 unique visitors on its first day. WebMonkey devoted an entire new post to it. Used in big
	industry websites like <u>A List Apart</u> , <u>Smashing Magazine</u> , <u>Mozilla Developer Network</u> , <u>CSS Tricks</u> and many others.
	·
FEB 2012	The CSS3 Test: High coverage testsuite for the most stable CSS3 modules.
	50,000 unique visitors on its launch (first two days). It has motivated browser vendors such as
	Mozilla or WebKit to support more CSS3 features to increase their scores on it.
DEC 2011	dabblet: An interactive CSS playground that saves to Github gists.
	Dabblet's release received enthusiastic feedback from the community, and was publicised by
	popular industry media like <u>Wired.com's WebMonkey</u> , <u>CSS-Tricks</u> , <u>Smashing Magazine</u> and
	others. During its first month, it received more than 65,000 unique visitors, 15,000 of which
	during its first two days.
OCT 2011	<u>-prefix-free</u> : A library that adds vendor prefixes to CSS using feature detection
	-prefix-free was featured in <u>Smashing Magazine twice</u> . Eric Meyer <u>said</u> about it "It's fantastic,
	top-notch work! Thank you for creating and sharing it.". Over 2,500 people have starred it on
	Github.
	Giriub.

SEP 2011	<u>cubic-bezier.com</u> : Direct manipulation of bezier-based easing functions The code from cubic-bezier.com was included in <u>Firefox</u> , and <u>Adobe's Brackets editor</u> .
APR 2011	<u>CSS3 Patterns Gallery</u> : Using CSS3 to generate background patterns My patterns gallery received lots of publicity. It was featured in Smashing Magazine multiple times and mentioned in conference talks and books by a number of industry leaders. It was used by Opera Software to fine-tune their CSS gradients implementation.

A lot more of my open source work can be found in my Github account.

EDUCATION

2014–2020 (Expected)	Ph.D in Computer Science (current GPA: 5.0/5.0) Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)
2007-2013	B.Sc. in Computer Science (GPA: 8.4/10, top 3%) Thesis: "Dabblet: A visual IDE for rapid prototyping of client-side web development", Advisor: Vasilis Vassalos Athens University of Economics and Business

ACADEMIC DISTINCTIONS

2014-2015	Paris Kanellakis Fellowship Award
2010	One of the 9 students (out of hundreds of applicants) that were selected by Hell.A.S. to attend classes at Stanford University for a week.
2000, 2001, 2002, 2003, 2004	Yearly distinctions in the Hellenic Mathematical Society contests, up to 2 nd place nationally. Qualification to its premilinary contest for Balkan Mathematical Olympiad in 2004.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

I have a broad understanding of the full Open Web Stack of technologies, including:

- CSS (including CSS3)
- JavaScript (ECMAScript), DOM & related APIs
- HTML5 and related APIs
- XML technologies, including SVG and MathML
- WAI-ARIA

I also have experience with a wide range of programming languages and technologies, including PHP, SQL, Java and many more.

LANGUAGES

■ **Greek**: Native

■ English: Very fluent

TOEFL score: 115/120, Certificate of Proficiency in English, University of Michigan, 2001

PROFESSIONAL INTERESTS

Open web standards, user experience, UI design, web development education, front-end web development, API design, web accessibility, technical writing, graphic design, color theory, typography

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Human-Computer Interaction, End user programming, Web architecture, Social computing, Data visualization

6/6